<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony of God, and his way, and worship against all the false wayes and worships of the vvorld. Also an answer to some of the false doctrines held forth, by a professed minister, in VVales; shewing the unsoundness of his former actions, and is found to be one, in the nature of the vvorld; which sometime he hath spoken against. With an answer to some queries; propounded by one, who is called an Anabaptist. / Given forth for no other end, but in love to the truth, as it is in Iesus: by Alex: Parker.</title>
            <author>Parker, Alexander, 1628-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E883_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866360</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866360</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118631</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118631)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E883[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony of God, and his way, and worship against all the false wayes and worships of the vvorld. Also an answer to some of the false doctrines held forth, by a professed minister, in VVales; shewing the unsoundness of his former actions, and is found to be one, in the nature of the vvorld; which sometime he hath spoken against. With an answer to some queries; propounded by one, who is called an Anabaptist. / Given forth for no other end, but in love to the truth, as it is in Iesus: by Alex: Parker.</title>
                  <author>Parker, Alexander, 1628-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londen, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A professed minister = Vavasor Powell; a response to some comments made by Powell at a conference held "in the publick meeting place at old Radnor in Wales".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July.14.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Powell, Vavasor, 1617-1670 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Independent churches --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118631:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Teſtimony of God, And his way, and worſhip againſt all the falſe wayes and worſhips of the VVorld.</p>
            <p>Alſo an anſwer to ſome of the falſe Doctrines held forth, by a profeſſed Miniſter, in VVales; ſhewing the unſoundneſs of his former actions, and is found to be one, in the nature of the VVorld; which ſometime he hath ſpoken againſt.</p>
            <p>WITH An anſwer to ſome Queries; propounded by one, who is called an Anabaptiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Given forth for no other end, but in love to the truth, as it is in Ieſus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY ALEX: PARKER.</p>
            <p>LONDEN, Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118631:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118631:2"/>
            <head>A Teſtimony of God, and his way, and worſhip, againſt all the falſe wayes and worſhip of the world.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD is pure and holy, and loves righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and his worſhip is a pure and a ſpiritual worſhip, not known to the world that lives in wickedneſs: the world by all their wiſdom and ſtudy cannot find out the mind of God, neither do they worſhip him in ſpirit, but are wondering and worſhipping the Beaſt, who have not found their names written in the book of life, and though they make a profeſſion of the name of God, yet are aliens and ſtrangers from the pure life and power of God, and ſo are climbing up another way and building up <hi>Babel,</hi> (a Tower to reach up to Heaven in their Heatheniſh and Babiloniſh wiſdom) where there is nothing but confuſion and ſtrife, one crying lo here is Chriſt, another crying lo there, one crying up his way to be the onely way, and counts all accurſed that are not in his way, and ſo the ſecond cries up his way, and ſo all the world lies in confuſion and wickedneſſe, ſtrife and debate, and though many have long been ſeeking after God, yet have not found him, becauſe they ſought him not in his own
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118631:3"/>way. Which is pure for ever; but by their own wit and wiſdom have gone about to know and find out the miſtery of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, &amp; ſo have walked &amp; gone on in the crooked wayes, and by paths of the world, and have deſpiſed that little thing within, which is the light of Jeſus that ſhines in the midſt of all this darkneſs, and reproves them in ſecret for their evil deeds, and ſhews them their confuſion, and oftentimes bring them to a ſtand, and ſome ſenſe or feeling of the deadneſs and emptineſs of all their profeſſion, and of their tottering building which is builded upon the ſand, and cannot ſtand in the fiery day of the fierce wrath and indignation of God, and when they daub up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſmooth words, crying the ordinances of Chriſt, and the Church of Chriſt, and the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and faith in Chriſt, and though they be wicked and ſinfull, and muſt be ſo while they live, yet Chriſt doth not impute their ſin unto them, they are juſtified in Chriſt, though they ſometime run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſin, and thus would make Chriſt a cloak for their ſin: yet ſtill the light of Chriſt teſtifies againſt them, and all their colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and painted outſide, and talking of juſtification, without holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life, will not bring them peace, but ſtill there is a cry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God for purity, and reproves them for their ſin and iniquity, and no peace there is to the wicked, as long as they act contrary to the meaſure of God, all their profeſſion and high notions, and glorious comprehenſions and guilded outſides, is but like unto <hi>Adams</hi> fig-leafe garment, and will not cover their nakedneſſe in the dreadfull and powerfull day of the Lord, the wicked ſhall be as the ſtuble, and ſhall be conſumed root and branch, all their crying Lord, Lord, will not avail them in that day, all their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, reading, praying, and the like (being found workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity) will do them no good, but this dreadfull ſentence from the Lord will be pronounced againſt them, <hi>Go curſed workers of iniquity, I know you not, depart from me, into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> Conſider of this all you carnall and formall Profeſſors, Prieſts and People, who talke ſo much of the name of God, drawing neer unto him with your lips and with your mouths, but your hearts goes after your covetouſneſſe and things of this world, which comes to an end and withers and fades away, and pleads againſt the power and purity of Godlyneſs; ſaying, none can ever be made free from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118631:3"/>ſin nor perfect in this world, but muſt continue in ſin or ſin in him while he lives, and ſo have made a Covenant with hell and with death, and no longer time will ſerve the devill your maſter whole ſervants you are, as long as you live in ſin) but terme of life; What will ye anſwer the Lord in that day, will then a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerve you, that you have not ſinned unto death, or that your ſin ſhall not be imputed to you? Shall not then the witneſſe of God in your own conſcience, which all along hath teſtified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, for your ungodly practiſes and reproved you for your ſecret evils? Shall it not ſtop your mouths and you ſhall ſtand ſpeechleſſe, and ſhall be made to confeſſe that God is juſt, and your condemnation juſt, who in your life time have rejected his counſell, and caſt his Law behind your backs, and have turned his grace into laſciviouſneſs, know this aſſuredly, this will be your portion at the latter day, for God is juſt and will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a juſt reward unto every one, according to their deeds done in the body whether they be good or whether they be evill; They that have improved their talents and done well, ſhall enter into the Lords joy: But thoſe who have ſleighted the Lords free love, which is freely tendred and have been careleſſe and negligent and have not improved, their tallents ſhall be caſt out from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and ſhall have their portion in the lake of utter darkneſſe, where there is weeping and wailing and gnaſhing of teeth: and this ſhall be the condemnation of all the world who hate the light, that Jeſus Chriſt hath enlightened them withall, and love their evill deeds better then the light: For this is the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world, (not becauſe light is not come,) but that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſſe rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evil, and ſo all the world lies under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation who are in the ſin and evill and deny the light, which gives the entrance into the Kingdoms of Chriſt, which ſtands in righteouſneſs, and no unrighteous one can enter, for no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance is made but through the death of ſin, and there is no death nor freedom from ſin, but only by the Son of God, there is no way but by him, no ſalvation but in him, no ſeparation from ſin nor reconciliation to God, but only by the Son o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, who is given of the Father a Covenant of light into the World, who doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world, and by this light is the Devils work ſeen, and by faith in him who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118631:4"/>hath given the light is the heart purified and the conſcience pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from dead works, and ſo the devils works comes to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, for, for this purpoſe was the Son of God made manifeſt that he might deſtroy the works of the devill; and the works of the devil are in the heart; for in the time of the night the devil the enemy of man, he hath wrought his works in the heart of man, and ſo hath wrought and begotten him into his image, to do his work, and ſo man becomes a ſervant to the devil, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging forth fruits of unrighteouſneſſe, and this is all done in the heart, the devil having gotten poſſeſſion, and ſits and rules as King in the heart of man; and there is the ground of all ſin, it a riſeth out of the heart, which is deceitful and deſperately wicked from thence ariſeth pride, envy, wrath, malice, murders, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, lying, ſwearing, adultery, fornication, covetouſneſs, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, tiranny and oppreſſion, and all other evills whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they have their ground and riſe from with in out of the heart, for there is no man tempted of God, but every man when he is tempted he is drawn a way of his own luſt, for luſt is conceived in the heart, and after it is conceived it brings forth ſin, and ſin being finiſhed brings forth death, and the wayes of ſin is death: and while ſin lodgeth and is regarded in the heart, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files the heart and ſeparates from God, and all the prayers and ſacrifices that are offered up unto God from an impure heart, are abomination to him; all outward ſhewes and outward clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, will not avail nor bring peace, as long as the ground and root of ſin remains within, for it is the heart which the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, as it is written my Son give me thy heart; ſo it is an inward work that every one muſt know and witneſſe, if ever you know true peace, and reſt, for as the devils work is within in the heart and defiles the heart, ſo muſt the work of Chriſt be within likewiſe, for the deſtroying of the devils works, and for the purifying of the heart, for this is the miſtery which hath been hid, and is hid from all wiſedom of the fleſh, and from all vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous eyes and venomous beaſts, and reveiled to the Babes and Lambs of God, who have laid down their Crowns at the feet of the Lamb, and have denied themſelves and the pomp and glory of this world, and do bear the dayly Croſs and deſpiſed the ſhame, and do love and walk in the light, which the world hates, and thereby are led out of darkneſſe, and the ungodly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118631:4"/>practiſes which the world lives in: into righteouſneſs and peace to exerciſe a good conſcience towards God and towards man; and this muſt every one own, if ever they own the living God, or a pure conſcience where the Miſtery of faith is held, they muſt own this light to guide them in the exerciſe of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: for this light is the eye, whereby a man comes to ſee himſelf and the root and ground of ſin, and untill man comes to own this light he never comes truly ſo ſee himſelf, and ſo is far from denying ſelf, for firſt a man muſt ſee himſelf before he can deny himſelf, and the light it is, that let a man ſee his ſin, and that he is driven from God, and out of union with God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his ſin: and it is ſin that ſeparate from God, and breaks the peace with God, for all have ſinned and come ſhort of the glory of God; all have gone aſtray (we our ſelves even as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) and have been wandring as Sheep without a Shepherd, but the Lord of Hoſts is riſen; and hath ſent forth his Son even Jeſus Chriſt the true Shepherd, who is gathering his Sheep into the fold where they ſhall lye down in peace, and none ſhall make them afraid; and if the Son make you free, then are you free indeed, but no freedom there is but only by him, whoſe bloud waſheth and cleanſeth from all ſin; and whereas it is ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>If we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us;</hi> This was ſpoken to a condition before confeſſion, as is plain to the Children of Light, for ſaith he, <hi>if we confeſſe our ſins he is faithfull and juſt to forgive our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs:</hi> he doth not ſay from part but from all, and this they witneſſed who were in the light, and hath fellowſhip with the Father and the Son, as is written, God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all, he that ſaith he hath fellowſhip with God and walks in darkneſs, is a liar, and doth not the truth; But if we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with another, and the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin; and him wee witneſſe, even Jeſus Chriſt the everlaſting Covenant of God, who makes free to the utmoſt all that come unto God by him; and wee teſtify againſt all thoſe that oppoſe the pure do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt Jeſus, and ſayes, none can be fully cleanſed from ſin while they live upon the earth, and ſo would make the bloud of Chriſt of none effect, which (whoſoever walketh
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118631:5"/>and abideth in the light of Chriſt, his bloud) cleanſeth from all ſin, for whoſoever abides in him, ſins not, he that ſinneth hath not ſeen him, neither known him, and this the Scripture decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and I bear teſtimony and ſet to my ſeal that it is true, for he that doth righteouſneſs is righteous, even as he is righteous, and hee that commits ſin is of the devill, for the devil ſinneth from the beginning: but whoſoever is born of God doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin, for his ſeed remaines in him, and he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God, and in this are the Children of God made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and the children of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vil, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. &amp;c. He that is born of God is the Son of God, and the Son of God doth not commit ſin; and except a man be born again, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God, for the firſt man is of the earth earthly, and minds earthly things, his joy and treaſure is there, in things that are below, delighting in the viſible things, his heart is there, his care and labour is for the things of this life, what to eat, what to drink, what to put on, how to become great in the earth, and by his earthly wiſedom which is from below, (which is ſenſual and deviliſh) he is plotting &amp; contriving to get great poſſeſſions, and to compaſte the earth to get himſelf a name in the earth, but cannot be ſatisfied, when he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed one piece of ground which he coveted after, preſently the luſt runs out again and covets more, but is never ſatisfied, and in this ſtate man is an enemy to God, and the thoughts of his heart are evill, and that continually, and notwithſtanding many times a true ſenſe and feeling of his ſad and miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is ariſing in him, and the witneſſe of God reproving him and calling him from his abominations and whoredoms, and many times brings him into ſome trouble, yet he ſleights his love and hates the reproof and goes on in his rebellious wayes, and ſo treaſures up to himſelf wrath, againſt the day of wrath and revellation of the righteous judgement of God, who will render a juſt reward unto him according to his deeds, and here lies all the ungodly world, driven from God, out of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, out of his peace, out of his preſence, out of his pure love and ſpiritual worſhip, and are loving and delighting in and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiping the creature more then the Creator: But the Saints and holy men of God, who came to witneſſe redemption and were in Covenant with God, and faith of his Son, had paſſed from death
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118631:5"/>to life, and they had put of the body of ſin, and the old man and his deeds, and were created anew, being born again of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall word, which liveth and abideth for ever; and their hearts was purified, and their conſciences purged from dead works, and ther bodies made fit Temples holy and pure for the Lord God to dwell in, and there was his worſhip, in the ſpirit, in his holy Temple, where there is no need of Sun Moon or of Candle, but the glory of the Lord fils the Temple, and this they witneſſed who were redeemed from the earth, and were in Chriſt Jeſus, where there union, joy, and fellowſhip was, where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumſition, nor uncircumſition Barbarian, Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian, bond nor free, but Chriſt is all and in all; and the ſame is the Lord our God, now working and bringing to paſſe even by his own power and outſtretched arm is he getting himſelf the victory, what we are, we are of and by him, he alone it is that worketh in us both to will and to do, by his own power made manifeſt in us, and worketh mightily in us, whereby wee are made willing to do his will and work, and this is all by his Son, who of God is made wiſdom, juſtification, ſanctification and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, he is made unto us all things, and through him we can do all things even through the Son of God, whom we know is come, and hath given us an underſtanding to know him that is true, and wee are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, who is our life, our joy, our ſtay and ſtrength, by whom we are freed from ſin, and from our vain converſations, which formerly we lived in; who hath broken the bond of iniquity, and ſet the oppreſſed free, to praiſe and glorify his name, who alone do praiſe him, the dead cannot praiſe him, it is the living, the living that praiſes him to whom be everlaſting praiſes and glory, world without end, Amen.</p>
            <p>So I ſay and declare that if any man ſay he hath no ſin before he come to confeſſe his ſin, and to witneſſe the power of God cleanſing him from his ſin, he doth dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive himſelf, and the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in his own conſcience will teſtify againſt him and be his condemnation: But where the living power of God is made manifeſt to purify and cleanſe, and to deſtroy the works of the devil, to burn up and conſume the old heavens and the old earth, which is curſed and brings forth curſed fruits: I ſay where the old is deſtroyed, and the new heaven and the new earth witneſſed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118631:6"/>wherein dwells righteouſneſs. Shall we deny the work of God? Not far be it from us, but to declare his marvailous works which he hath wrought in our dayes, to ages and generations to come that they may dread and fear the name of our God, and to others who ſit in darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death, who are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring aſtray as ſheep without a Shepherd, and are feeding upon the husk, and ſpending their money for that which is not bread, and their labour for that which doth not ſatisfy: freely from the bowels of tender love to their ſoules, do we declare what the Lord hath done for our ſoules, that they might return home into the Fathers houſe, where there is bread enough to ſatisfy the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry thirſting ſoul, that every one may eat their own bread, and ſit under their own vine, and have union and feilowſhip with us in our fathers love for evermore. So in the name of the Lord I do warn all people who read theſe lines, to repent and ceaſe from all their ſins and abominations, which formerly they have lived in, and from all the falſe and Idolatrous worſhips of the world, which a long time ye have followed, and thereby have been deceived and led captive laden with ſin, but have not come to the true knowledg of God, but are ſtill in their old crooked and perverſe nature, and knows not the Croſſe of Chriſt, nor the yoke nor the bridle to the tongue, but are at eaſe in the fleſh, and can ſpeake their own words, and think their own thoughts, and do their own works; I ſay return, return, and hearken diligently to the voyce of the Son of God, which cryes for purity and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, without which none can ſee God, that thereby your ſoules may live, and may feed upon the dayly bread in the Fathers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, which whoſoever eats of this bread ſhal never hunger, and he that drinks of this cup ſhall never thirſt; but it ſhall be a well of living water, ſpringing up unto eternal life: ſo every one wayt in the meaſure of light, which from Chriſt you have received for the appearance of Chriſt in you, that his life may be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in your mortal bodies: for this is the command of God, <hi>This is my beloved Son hear him;</hi> and Chriſt, the Son calls, and ſays, <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden, take my yoke upon you, and learn of me, I am meek and lowly in ſpirit, and you ſhall find rest to your ſoules.</hi> So all people come freely, his love is freely tendred to you, ſleight not the tender profers of his love, but come forth and ſeparate your ſelves, and touch no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118631:6"/>unclean thing and the Lord will receive you, and will be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto you, and you ſhall be his Sons and Daughters, mind the pure and ſtill voyce, that thereby you may be led into the pure life, and pure union and love of the children of light; for if you neglect ſuch great ſalvation, woe will be your portion for ever. There ore whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e you have the light believe in the light, and work while it is day, before the dreadfull night of darkneſs come when none can work.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By one who hath ſeen the deadneſs and emptineſs of all the formal worſhips and formal profeſſion that ſtands in the will of man act d in mans will, who is returned back into his fathers houſe, and there dwels in reſt and peace, and hath ceaſed from his own work; written forth in the bowels of love to captive and weary ſouls, who have long been toſſed to and fro, by following the changeable doctrine of men, but are not ſatisfied that they may return home into the fathers houſe with me, where they ſhall find ſatisfaction and plenteous redemption, where all the Saints are one, and their food one, and have a new name written, which none knows nor can read but thoſe that hath it: and there my name is written in the Spiritual book of life, and they that are there do it read and know. Who am known to the World by the name of <hi>ALEX: PARKER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118631:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An anſwer to ſome of the falſe doctrines, held forth by one</hi> Vavaſar Powel, <hi>who is called a Master and a Minister, and ſomething further occaſioned by ſome conference held with the ſaid</hi> Vavaſar, <hi>in the publick meeting place at old</hi> Rad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor <hi>in</hi> Wales; <hi>ſhewing the unſoundneſs of his ſormation: and to be one in nature and rage with all the Pariſh Teachers, which hee hath ſo much tryed againſt written for the ſake of the ſimple ones, that they may be awarned and fore-armed to keep out of his ſnare.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GReat hath been and is the rage of the world &amp; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of truth, againſt the life and power of truth where-ever it was made manifeſt in former generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as it is now in this generation againſt the deſpiſed people of God, whom the Lord hath owned, and made his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er manifeſt, whom the ſcorners that knows not God do call Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, eſpecially the Prieſts, and they who profeſſe themſelves Teachers of the Nations, who in their high places utters forth their ſpight and venome, and incenſing their hearts againſt them, as though they were a people not worthy to live: Amongſt whom one who is called Mr. <hi>Vavaſar Powel,</hi> who is called a Teacher, and much ſet up and adored by the blind Profeſſors in <hi>Wales</hi> and other parts, who is looked upon to be one above the reſt and ſeparated from them, yet in perſecution &amp; rage joyn with them, and exceeds many of them in railing, backbiting, and caſiling many falſe aſperſions upon the innocent people and harmleſſe Lambs of Chriſt, in his high place uttering forth ſuch
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118631:7"/>things as are not fit to be mentioned by any that profeſſes the name of God, much leſſe by one who profeſſes himſelf a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God. And I being in thoſe parts of <hi>Wales,</hi> and hearing of his railing accuſations againſt the people of God, in moſt places where he came, and I amongſt the reſt of my b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ethren was falſly accuſed and ſlandered by ſome of his hearers, and I being innocent, and the Lords truth cleer from all thoſe things falſly charged upon us was moved of the Lord to go to old <hi>Radnor</hi> in <hi>VVales</hi> on the 5. day of the 3. month called May 1656. to ſtand a witneſs for the living truth of God againſt <hi>Powel</hi> and all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the truth, and that day he the ſaid <hi>Powel</hi> was found in the ſteps of the Scribes and Phariſees, whom our Lord Jeſus Chriſt cried woe againſt, he went up into the high place, and ſtood praying in the Sinagogue as the Scribes and Phariſees did, he is called of men Maſter, contrary to the command of Chriſt to his Miniſters, who ſaith unto his, be not ye called of men Maſter, for ye have but one Maſter even Chriſt, and ye are brethren; but <hi>Vavaſar Powell</hi> is called of men Maſter, contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, which none of his true Miniſters were; and ſo under the woe. The true Miniſters of God had the Spirit of God, and had ſalt in themſelves to ſavour withall, and they knew who were the true Miniſters of God, and who were deceivers even by the Spirit of God that was in them, and they prayed by the Spirit of God. But <hi>Vavaſar Powel</hi> in this is ſhort of the true Miniſters; for he in his prayer deſired that the Lord would diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ſhew them, who his true Miniſters were, and who were deceivers, and in this thing he is made manifeſt, and doth plainly appear that he prayed not by the Spirit of God, who cannot diſcern the true Miniſters from the deceivers, and ſo hath not ſalt in himſelf to ſavour withall, but hath loſt his honour and is good for nothing, but to be caſt out and trodden under foot of man, for the Spirit of the Lord doth diſcern and diſcover, and put a difference between the precious and the vile, and betwixt the true Miniſters and the deceivers; in this he is found contrary to the true Miniſters of God. He ſaid and held forth, that every naturall man had a fourfold light, but denyed that he had any light in him that was pure, to lead him to Chriſt. He ſaid that all men were wholy in darkneſſe, and nothing at all of the ſpiritual light in them, (or words to that effect) and yet ſaid that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118631:8"/>every naturall man had a talent which if he did not improve was his condemnation. Now all whoſe eyes are in any meaſure opened may ſee his confuſion, for if the natural man have a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and the talent be natural, then a natural man that improves his natural talent, may enter into the Lords joy: as is plain in Scripture, for he that had five talents gained other five, and he that had two he gained other two; and the Lord calling them to account pronounces to them well done good and faithful ſervants enter into your Maſters joy; but the ſlothful ſervant who did not improve his talent was caſt out, but the talent was taken from him, and given to him that had improved: And in this thing I ſtand a witheſſe againſt Mr. <hi>Powell</hi> ſo called, and do witneſſe to Jeſus the True Light, the ſame which <hi>Iohn</hi> bare teſtimony of, who lighteth every one that cometh into the world who is pure and ſpiritual, in whom is life, and the life is the light of men, and his life is ſpiritual, and ſo is his light, which the dark world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend, for this is the condemnation of the world who love their evill deeds and hate the light: for every one that doth truth, he loveth the light, and brings his deeds to the light, and thereby is led out of darkneſſe by oaths and crooked wayes, and ſo ſhall have the light of life: But he that doth evil he hateth the light, and will not bring his deeds to the light, becauſe he knows the light will reprove him, and ſo the light is his condemnation, and is the ſame and one with that, which is the ſalvation of the believer: ſo I ſay that the light is one in the believer, as in the unbeliever, according to meaſure as the talents were one, given to the ſlothfull as well as the faithfull, and the talents were pure, and thoſe who improved them entred into joy, and he that did not was caſt out into utter darkneſſe, but the talent was not, for it was taken from him, and given to him that had, &amp;c. So this is the condemnation of the world and all the ungodly ones who live in ungodlineſſe, they are condemned by the light, for the light is pure, and that which reproves and makes manifeſt ſin, is light, as the Apoſtle declares, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.13. and this light ſhews ſin before the action of it, it ſhews it in its riſe and conception, before it come to action, if there be but an evil thought, or an evill motion, or an evil deſire, or any evill intent the light diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers it, and waiting in the light and believing in Chriſt, who hath given the light, the victory is obtained, for the true faith purifies
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118631:8"/>the heart, and gives victory over the world, and without faith it is not poſſible to pleaſe God, and <hi>Paul</hi> who was a true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God he was ſent to open the blind eyes, (not to bring them eyes) but to open that eye which the God of the world had blinded, and ſo to turn them from darkneſſe unto light, and from the power of Satan unto God that they might receive forgiveneſs of ſins, and an inheritance a mongſt them that are ſanctified by faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and he preached Jeſus Chriſt which was within the Saints their hope of glory, teaching and exhorting every man in all wiſedom, that they might preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27, 28. And when Chriſt aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he gave ſome Apoſtles and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12. this is the pure doctrine of Chriſt Jeſus, and that which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf taught, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. Be ye perfect as your Father which is in Heaven is perfect. But this doctrine <hi>Powell,</hi> and all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Teachers do oppoſe, and ſo manifeſt themſelves to bee Anti-Chriſt a gainſt Chriſt and his true Miniſters, and ſerve ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maſter which is the Devil whoſe work they are doing, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtrongly for his Kingdom, which ſtands in ſin and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and ſayes none can be perfect while they live upon the earth, this with them is an impoſſible thing, but with God all things are poſſible, and the true Miniſters of God believe it and do earneſtly contend for this faith, and for their Maſter Chriſt and his Kingdom, which ſtands in righteouſneſſe, purity and perfection, and no unrighteous one, nor imperfect one can enter into it, then woe to them that live in ſin while they are upon earth, their end will be in the lake of endleſſe miſery, and this ſhall <hi>Powell</hi> and all the <hi>Antixtian Bablers</hi> one day wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: And <hi>Powell</hi> in words this did preach, that no unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous one could enter into the Kingdom of God, and as long as any one ſin was alive in any, though never ſo little the devil could keep them by one, as well as by many bringing this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, that if a fiſher-man had catched hold of a fiſh, and the fiſh had broken two of his haires, yet by one he might catch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118631:9"/>him; ſo ſaith he all ſin muſt be deſtroyed, and the houſe clean ſwept, and afterward he pleaded for ſin and ſaid, none could be without ſin, nor perfect while he lived (ſee his confuſion) by this doctrine a man muſt never be without the devill in him, for all ſin is of the devill, and while ſin is within; the devill is with in. But the true Miniſters of God who came to witneſſe Chriſt Ieſus and his life and power, made manifeſt in them, did witneſſe the devills work deſtroyed, and conſumed by his word, which was as a fire in them, and the Miniſters of Chriſt do witneſſe the ſame now, by the ſame living power by which the devils works comes to be deſtroyed, and the Son of God witneſſed who makes free from ſin, and if the Son make you free, then are you free indeed; and in this Mr. <hi>Powell,</hi> ſo called, is out of the doctrine of Chriſt, and contrary to his true Miniſters. Further the ſaid <hi>Powell</hi> in the preſence of many people, did affirm that the Scriptures were the foundation and ground of Faith; which thing I did deny, and did teſtify a gainſt him for blaſphemy, and do ſtill affirm the ſame, that whoſoever doth ſay and teach that the Scripture is the foundation of Faith, is a liar and a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and doth lay another foundation contrary to the Apoſtles, as is teſtifyed of in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>For no other foundation can any man lay, then that is laid, which is Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and the ſame do I witneſſe and no other: and here <hi>Powell</hi> muſt either confeſſe the Scriptures to be Chriſt, or elſe he layeth another foundation, contrary to that which all the holy men of God were built upon, which had faith before the Scriptures were written. <hi>Abel</hi> had faith before the Scripture was written, and <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and many others mentioned and ſpoken of in the Scripture, they had faith and were built upon the rock, even Ieſus Chriſt, who was before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, and before the letter or writing was, who was before the world was, who is the ſame yeſterday to day and for ever, who is the ground and foundation of faith: And <hi>Powell,</hi> and all the Pariſh Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in <hi>England</hi> and elſe where, that ſays the Scriptures are the foundation, are in the blaſphemy and error, and his and their fouudation will not ſtand in the day of the Lord, which ſhall burn up their works as hay and ſtuble, and this ſhall <hi>Powell</hi> one day witneſſe to be truth to him, and all others who lay another foundation, which is but ſandy, and cannot ſtand, but great
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118631:9"/>ſhall be the fall of it, when the ſtorm and tempeſt doth ariſe; and in this the ſaid called Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> is contrary to the true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and the Scriptures ſhall be a teſtimony againſt him and his blaſphemy, who ſets the Scriptures in the place of Chriſt, which onely teſtify of Chriſt, but are not Chriſt; and the Scriptures declare of the foundation of faith Ieſus Chriſt, but the Scriptures are not the foundation Chriſt Jeſus, neither did any of the Miniſters of Chriſt ever call the Scriptures the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ground of faith; but witneſſed and declared Chriſt to be the Author and the finiſher of their faith, and the rock and foundation which they were built upon, and the ſame do I teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy of, even Jeſus Chriſt, who was from the beginning, and the ſame to day and for ever, who was the rock in former ages, and the ground of their faith, and the rock of this age, and ſo the rock of ages, and the ground and foundation, and the Author, and finiſher of our faith, to whom be all honour and glory of and from all that know him for evermore.</p>
            <p>And further as I was ſpeaking of the word of the Lord, and its power and effect, and that the Holy men of God who came to witneſſe the word of the Lord, then knew it not by hearſay from others, but by its powerfull operation in them, by which word their hearts was purifyed and cleanſed, which word was within them as a fire to burn up and conſume the works of the devill, and as a hammar to break the hard heart, and this word was not far of, as the Apoſtle teſtifieth, ſay not in thy heart who ſhall aſcend up into Heaven to fetch Chriſt from above, or go down into the deep to fetch him from below, but the word is nigh thee in thy heart and in thy mouth, and this is the word of faith that we preach, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. and this word was within them, and wrought powerfully in them, which they witneſſed to be quick and powerfull ſharper then a two edged ſword; and thoſe who know not this living and powerfull word within them puts the letter for the word and calls that the word; and when I ſpoke theſe words, the ſaid <hi>Powell</hi> ſaid unto me, Is not the Scriptures called the word of God? And then I ſaid unto him, is it the word of God (for it hath long been called ſo by ignorants, that knows not God and his word) and he affirmed, and ſaid it was, and was put to prove it, and he brought two places of Scriptures,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118631:10"/>but neither place did ſay that the Scriptures was the word of God, but declared of the word: and then <hi>Powell</hi> ſaid to his hearers, we will leave them heare, they deny the Scriptures to be the word of God; and ſome of his hearers were very ready to receive it, and cryed out they deny the Scripture; whereupon I ſpoke to them and wiſhed to be moderate and hear with patience, and do not accuſe falſly. That becauſe we cannot call the Scriptures by the name of Chriſt, do we therefore deny the Scripture? No, far be it from us, to deny it, for if I ſhould deny its teſtimony, I ſhould deny my own life; and I ſaid, I own it to be a true declaration of that word that was in them that ſpoke it forth, and it was the word of the Lord to them and in them that ſpoke it forth; but for ungodly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy men to talk of their words, and not live in their life, are theeves that ſteales the word from their neighbour; and ſome of the people ſaid, was it the word of the Lord to them and not to us? And this they would not hear; and then I inſtanced ſome Scriptures to them, how that the word of the Lord came to the true Prophets, and they ſpoke the word of the Lord as they had received it from the mouth of the Lord; and after it was ſpoken forth, the falſe Prophets ſtole the true Prophets words, and they ſaid, thus ſaith the Lord, when the Lord never ſpoke to them, and ſo run when the Lord never ſent them, and therefore they did not profit the people at all. And this further I ſay, that as it was then even ſo it is now in theſe our dayes prond men, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous men, heady and high minded men, and men that followes pleaſures and are lovers thereof, more then lovers of God, and envyous men, and men of ſtrife and railers, back-biters, ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and falſe accuſers, and ſuch like ungodly and unholy men, have gotten the Scriptures, the good words which the holy men of God ſpoke forth from the holy and pure word of God, which was within them, which was (and is) ſpiritual and inviſible, and endures for ever, ſuch ungodly men aforementioned, have gotten the declaration, and are talking of the fame of God, but are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the living life and power of God, and they fay this ſaith the Lord, or hearken to the word of the Lord as you ſhall find it written in ſuch a chapter and ſuch a verſe; and ſo uſe their tongues and ſay, the Lord ſaith (as the falſe Prophets did) when the Lord never ſpake to them, and ſo have gotten a form of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118631:10"/>but want the life and power, and leads ſilly (men and) women captive, laden with ſin and led away with divers luſts ever learning, but never able to come to the true knowledge of God: ſo I ſay that many may have the Scriptures (which were given forth from them who knew the voyce and word of God) and know not neither have heard the voyce of God nor his word, but onely the ſound or frame of it: for the <hi>Iews</hi> who had the Scriptures, <hi>Moſes</hi> writings, and the Prophets, and could ſpeake much of them, and often heard them read, and yet Chriſt tells them plainly, they had neither heard his voyce at any time, nor ſeen his ſhape, for they had not the word of God abiding in them for whom the Father had ſent they did not believe, and there Chriſt himſelf calls them Scriptures which teſtify of him, but he doth not call them the Word of God; for if they had been the Word of God, then the <hi>Iews</hi> had heard the word of God, but Chriſt tells them they had not at any time heard the voyce of God, neither was the word of God abiding in them: as it is written, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.37, 38, 39. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And now a few words concerning the word of God, from Scripture teſtimony which the Holy men of God ſpoke forth, and ſo witneſſes to the ſame eternall word, which I bear teſtimony of, which was in the beginning before all time, by which the Heavens and the earth were made, and are upheld by the word of his power, as it is written, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. And the word of the Lord is ſpiritual and endures for ever, it is as a fire and as a hammer that breaks the rocks in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The word of God is quick and powerful, ſharper then any two edged ſword, and pearces even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23.25. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.29. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.12. But the Scriptures or writings were nor in the beginning before all time: but were ſince the beginning in time, neither were the Heavens made by the Scriptures, not are all things upheld by the Scripture, neither do they endure for ever; but they are viſible and in times paſſed away, but the word of the Lord which the Scriptures declare of, is ſpirituall, and ſhall endure for ever: The Scriptures or writings are not as a fire, but with fire may be burnt, as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> his roll was burnt, but the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118631:11"/>word of the Lord cannot be burnt, for by the living word ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Roll was written: The Scriptures or writings are not as a hammar, but with a hammar may be beaten to pieces, neither is the Scriptures quick, nor ſharper then a two edged ſword; but they are dead, and with a two edged ſword may be cut to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, behold your ignorance you carnall Profeſſors, whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings are ſo dark, and your eyes ſo blind that you ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at noon day, and ſo cannot put a difference between the precious and the vile, nor between the living word and the dead letter, but ſets the letter in the place of Chriſt, as <hi>Vavaſar Powel</hi> doth, who calls the Scriptures the Foundation of Faith, and the Word of God: when plain Scripture doth teſtify againſt him, and witneſſeth Chriſt to be the Foundation and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour and finiſher of Faith, whoſe name is called the Word, of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19, 13. Many other Scriptures I might bring that witneſſes of the Word of God, for all the whole Scriptures being given forth from the word, declare of the word, and ſo they are called by the Miniſters of the word, <hi>Luke</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>But it hath been a common thing amongſt the Profeſſours of our time, becauſe wee do not, nay dare not ſet the Scriptures in the place of Chriſt, nor call them by his name, to accuſe us for denying of the Scriptures, but their accuſation wee do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and let our lives and converſations which wee live in Chriſt Jeſus, be witneſſes for the Lord and for us herein, and I appeal to the conſcience of all the honeſt hearted in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to judge, whether thoſe who talk ſo much of Scripture, and calls it the Word of God and their Rule to walk by: and they themſelves live in pride and covetouſneſſe, ſtrife and envy, wrath, malice, ſtubborneſſe and croſneſſe, backbiting and ſpeaking evill one of another behind their backs, fooliſh jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, idle communication, vain ſports and pleaſures, and in the cuſtomes and faſhions of the world, little or nor at all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from them in any thing but in words, which things the Scripture teſtifies againſt or thoſe who live in the fear of God in meekneſſe and humility, and cannot faſhion themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the world, nor uſe the vain cuſtomes and traditions of men, who cannot bow to the rich, nor reſpect the perſons
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118631:11"/>of thoſe who were the gay cloathing and the gold Ring, no more then the poor man in the vile Rayment, which of theſe doth deny the Scriptures, thoſe who talke of them, and live not in the life of them: or thoſe whoſe lives and converſations are according to them, let the wiſe in heart Judge.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118631:12"/>
            <head>An anſwer to ſome Queries given to my hands, which were propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by one who goes under the name of an Anabaptiſt, living in <hi>Shrewsbury.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SOme Queries I have received from one who ſubſcribes his name <hi>Richard Stephens,</hi> wherein he ſaith the intent of his writing is to be better informed in things wherein he is not ſatisfied. But in the Light of Jeſus he is comprehended, and ſeen to be of that Generation, who cryed up the Commands and the Ordinances of God, as Temple, Sabbath, Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Prieſts, Sacrifices, Scriptures and the like, and ſaid they were of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and God was their Father, and they builded the Tombs of the Prophets, and garniſhed the ſepulchre of the righteous, and condemned their fore-fathers, ſaving, if we had lived in their dayes, we would not have killed the Prophets, and yet theſe crucified the Son of God, and they did not believe in him, who was the light, the Covenant of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſum and ſubſtance of thoſe things which they upheld, which were but figures, tipes and ſhadows, yet in their time Commands of God, and were to bee obſerved and kept, yet thoſe who had theſe outward Commands, did not believe in the Light, but were by (Chriſt) the Light cryed woe againſt, and thoſe who believed in the Light and followed Chriſt, denyed thoſe outward Commands, and had no Scripture for it, but the teſtimony of the light within them; which was a hard thing in thoſe times to deny the Commands in the letters; for the Jews and Chief Prieſts had Scripture to uphold them; and counted the Apoſtles deceivers, and a curſed people that knew not the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118631:12"/>Law: But by the mighty power of God they were carried on and witneſſed againſt the outward Commands, and cryed againſt them that upheld them: and witneſſed the Commands of God, and the worſhip of God in the ſpirit; and their bodies wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Holy Ghoſt, and God dwelt in them; ſo the new Covenant they witneſſed the Law of God written in their hearts, and the ſpirit put in the inward parts, which was their guide in the ſpiritual worſhip, and theſe denyed thoſe things which once were Commands of God, which were outward and typical, and it was no breach of the Commands of God to them, but obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the commands of the Spirit of God in them, by which they witneſſed againſt the ſhadows, and witneſſed the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: And a generation there is now (of which this man that gave forth theſe Queries is one) who hath gotten the good words (the Scriptures) and painted themſelves over with a covering, like the ſpirit, but is not the ſpirit; and theſe cry up the Church of Chriſt, and the ordinances of Chriſt, and condemnes the Jewes their fore-fathers for crucifying of Chriſt, and yet they are found in the ſame nature, who deny the light and counts them deceivers and a curſed generation who are in the light, who (with the light) deny their imitated Churches, and taken on commands, which it no more but a will worſhip, and a ſelf righteouſneſſe which ſtands in the will of man, which is as fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy rags and as menſtruous cloathes; ſeen they are and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the light of Chriſt to be under the woe out of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of our God; and here is the ground of all the ſects and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and the many Religions: Man living in his will, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Scriptures which came not by the will of man, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to mans will, here man in his will is giving his pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vate meanings and interpretations, and one he gives one meaning to the Scriptures, and ſets up a Religion and a worſhip of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his meaning, and conceiving from the letter of the Scripture in his will; Another he gives another meaning, and ſets up another worſhip and a Religion, according to his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and conceiving from the Scriptures: and ſo a third gives his meaning, and ſo are divided into many ſects and opinions; and theſe are the <hi>Babel</hi> builders, one building up a wall, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther daubing with untempered morter, and theſe are out of the faith and union of the Saints who walk in the light, and have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118631:13"/>union and fellowſhip in the ſpirit of love, written in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heart, and ſo are all of one heart: But the other who ſtands in their wills, and imitates and takes on commands in their own wills, as their imaginations thoughts and conceivings leads them, are not all of one heart, but are divided, and ſome ſprinkle water on the face of a child, and calls that Baptizme; and others deny that, and are dipped over head and ears in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and calls that Baptizme, and then they call themſelves Beleevers and Saints, and ſo run to the letter of the Scripture, and reading with a wrong eye, are ſtill in confuſion, and more and more diviſions there is a mongſt them, ſome are called free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willers, or that hold generall redemption (that Chriſt died for all) and ſome are called particulars, that hold that ſome are ordained to ſalvation, and ſome to condemnation before they have done good or evill, and theſe deny one another and hold one another accurſed, yet all are dipped in the water: ſome are divided about that which they call the Lords ſupper, and about breaking of the bread, ſome will break it themſelves, and ſome will eat it as a ſupper; ſome will ſup before they eat it, ſome will have it in an upper chamber, ſome are for laying on of hands, and ſome will not: and many other things there are which breakes their union, and thus they are divided in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons Kingdom, tearing and rending one another like dogs and ſwine, falling out about the husks. But the Saints who are led by the light of the Son of God (out of Babylon) into the fold, do feed upon the bread of life in the Fathers houſe, where there is no want, but fulneſſe where the preſence of the Lord is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, and the holy and innocent ones who are waſhed and cleanſed in the bloud of the Lamb, rejoyce in his preſence who are Baptized into Chriſt and have put on Chriſt, whoſe hearts are purified and conſcience purged from dead works, theſe are Chriſtians: But to ſprinkle water on the face of a child doth not make it a Chriſtian, or to be dipped over head and eares in water doth not waſh and cleanſe from ſin; for hee is not a Chriſtian which is one outward which hath the name only, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is that the Baptizme which is outward with the water: But he is a Chriſtian which is in Chriſt a new Creature, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizme is that of the ſpirit, having the heart ſprinkled from an evill conſcience, and the body waſhed with pure water, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118631:13"/>this Baptizme I own and witneſſe unto, and deny all imitatour who have not a command from God, as they had that gave forth the Scriptures. Yet this I ſay, if any one now have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Chriſt to go and Baptize with water: or if any out of tenderneſſe of Conſcience do ſuch a thing, I do not deny it, nor judge them for it: But I was not ſent to Baptize but to preach the Goſpel, and it is no breach of Chriſts command, nor denying his ordinances in not Baptizing, not being commiſſioned by him to Baptize, for it is neither dipping nor ſprinkling, or not dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that availes any thing but a new Creature, ſo to deny that which was a command of Chriſt to ſome, being but outward, it not being a command by Chriſt unto us, is no breach of Chriſts command, no more then it was in the Apoſtles in denying the outward commands, as Temple, Sabbath, Circumſition, and the like, which were commands in their time and place, and wee own them, and all the commands of God mentioned in the Scriptures by the ſame ſpirit which gave them forth: which ſpirit was the Saints Rule before the Scriptures were written, and their Rule who gave forth the Scripture, and the Saints Rule now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture, owning all things in their time and place as the Scripture declares of, and though we be counted as deceivers, yet true, it is no more but what the Miniſters of Chriſt undergone from that generation, who were high in knowledge as doctours, chief Prieſts and learned Rabbies, yet by all their learning and Scripture knowledge they knew not the miſtery, but counted the Croſſe of Chriſt fooliſhneſſe; as it is now by this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Scripture learned ones and univerſity men, by all their learning and ſtudy the miſtery of Godlineſſe they know not, but counts them an ignorant people to whom the Lord hath made known himſelf in meaſure, and reveiled his ſecrets unto, and counts them as a people not worthy to live; I ſay amongſt that generation that cryes up the commands of Chriſt in words I find this man querying without. But for the ſimple ones ſake who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſatisfied, I have written this in anſwer to his queries, that their minds may be informed, and from the darkneſſe they may be turned to the true light of leſus, which opens the dark un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and leads out of darkneſſe to follow Chriſt in the pure path of life, which whoſoever follows ſhall not abide in darkneſſe, but ſhall have the light of life.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118631:14"/>
            <p>Query the I. <hi>Whether you do own the New Teſtament with the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles unto the Churches, to be a true te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the ſpirit of the Lord, yea or nay: And if they be whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they not given forth as a Rule unto the Churches to walk by, and if they were not given forth as a Rule, then where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were they given forth, and what uſe were they of unto the Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The New Teſtament we do own and witneſſe, which is the Law of God written in our hearts, and the ſpirit put in the inward parts, whereby we are gathered together into the fold, and are fed with living refreſhments in the boſome of our Fathers love, which ſpirit was and is a Rule and guide unto the Saints, and thereby are taught of God in ſpirit, and do worſhip him in ſpirit, according to his promiſe, which promiſe is now fulfilled and fulfilling to his praiſe and glory, to whom all glory belongs for evermore: And the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles to the Churches we own to be a true teſtimony given forth from the ſpirit of the Lord, and was the word of the Lord in them and to them, to whom they were written for the edifying and building them up in their moſt holy faith, which faith was within them, a miſtery held in a pure conſcience; and their Rule and guid was within them, and all that was written or declared by the holy men of God, it was to bring them to the pure worſhip of God within, in the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> II. <hi>Whether the Scriptures be of any uſe unto any people now in this generation; and if they are then whether the Ordinances therein conteyned, be to be practiſed by ſuch a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as beleeve in the Lord Ieſus with all their hearts, yea or nay? And if they are not to be practiſed then when and where were they aboliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Scriptures are not of any private interpretation, neither (came by) mans will, but holy men of God ſpoke them forth as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt, and they are of uſe, for they were given forth to be read to be believed on to bee practiſed and fulfilled, but not to make a trade on, nor for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men with their vain and proud minds to talk on, but let every one that names the name of Chriſt depart from iniquity, and as iniquity is departed from, and the fear of God placed in the heart, it keepes the heart cleare, and ſo the pure wiſdom
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118631:14"/>from above, is received into the pure heart, and the pure in heart are bleſſed and ſhall ſee God who is light, and the Ordinances of God are ſeen in the light and led into by the light, but the darkneſſe cannot comprehend the light, nor all the wiſedom of the world, and ſuch puts darkneſſe for light, and light for dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and calls the ordinances and traditions of men the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, and ſo would make the word of God of none effect by their traditions; for they are the Sons of God who are led and guided by the Spirit of God, and ſuch denyes the ſhadows who witneſſe the ſubſtance, for if ye be dead with Chriſt from the Rudiments of the world, why, as though living in the world are ye ſubject to ordinances: God is a Spirit, and his ordinances are ſpiritual in the Goſpel Adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> III. <hi>Whether or no they are not bleſſed that do obſerve to do all the Ordinances and the Commands of the Lord Chriſt therein conteyned, yea or nay, and if they are then whether are not they a curſed generation of men, that do not obſerve to do them, but to teach men to break them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are bleſſed that do obſerve all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord Chriſt, that they may have right unto the tree of life, and may enter in through the gate into the City: But to that in thy conſcience do I ſpeak, art thou one that doſt obſerve al the Commandments of the Lord Chriſt, art thou brought to yea and nay in thy communication, art thou brought to do to all men as thou would have them to do unto thee? Doth not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in thy conſcience teſtify againſt thee, and let thee ſee the contrary? If any one ſue thee at the Law and take away the Coat, let him have thy Cloak alſo, doſt thou obey this command, or doſt thou not rather go quite contrary, inſtead of letting him have thy Cloak with thy Coat, would not thou go to Law with him before hee ſhould have thy Coat? To that in thy conſcience do I ſpeak; if one ſmite thee on one cheek, doſt thou turn the other, or would not ſomething in thee ariſe to ſmite again? Search and examine, and if upon ſearch thou be found a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſour, then art not thou one of the curſed generation that doſt not obſerve to do all the commands of the Lord Chriſt; which thoſe whom thou art ſmiting &amp; warring againſt through the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God working in them, are able and brought to obſerve, &amp; are of the bleſſed generation, to whom all the promiſes of God are due.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118631:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> IV. <hi>Whether there be any other Goſpel then that which was declared and teſtified of unto the world, by Chriſt and his Diſciples, which is left upon record unto us in this our genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Scriptures of Truth, yea or nay? And whether this that you declare be the ſame that Christ and his Apoſtles did declare unto the Saints in their generation both for matter and manner?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no other Goſpel but that which was declared and teſtified of by Chriſt and his Diſciples; and the ſame Goſpel do we preach and no other, which is a miſtery not known to the world, which cannot be contained in a book nor written in letters, for that which is written by <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> is but a declaration, and that may be bought and ſold for money: But the Goſpel cannot be bought and ſold for money, for it is the power of God unto ſalvation to every one that beleeves, and thoſe that witneſſed the Goſpel were freed from ſin, and had remiſſion of their ſins: But many have the Scriptures, but have not the power of God, but are alive unto ſin; and here thou haſt much manifeſted thy folly and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who would have the Goſpel conteined in a book, which all the books in the world cannot conteyn; which Goſpel and glad tydings is now witneſſed by the Children of Light, free pardon of ſin by Jeſus Chriſt, who is come to take away ſin; Glory and honour and everlaſting praiſes to his Holy and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full name for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> V. <hi>Whether the Apoſtles of Chriſt which wrote the Epiſtles unto the Churches, and the Saints in that generation had not as much of the light of Chriſt within them as any have now in this generation, yea or nay? And wherefore were the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles written, or did the Apoſtles write needleſſe things, or thy did they not onely call upon them to mind the light which was within them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Concerning the Apoſtles and the Saints, having as much of the light of Chriſt within them, as any have, now it little concernes thee or any one elſe, I leave it to him from whence all light comes, who is the ſame now as ever, and changes not, Jeſus Chriſt the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever, and gives to every one light, according as it pleaſeth him, which light the Prophets, and Apoſtles, and Holy men of God, did witneſſe in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118631:15"/>them; from which they write, and did not write needleſſe things, but exhorted to take heed to the light which was within them, which was and is a miſtery: we have alſo a more ſure word of Propheſie, unto which ye do well to take heed as unto a light ſhining in a dark place untill the day dawn, and the day ſtar ariſe in your hearts; The word is light, and the word was within them, nigh in their hearts; the Law is light, and the Law was within written in their hearts; the ſpirit is light, and it was within them to whom the Epiſtles were written; and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven is light, and it was within though not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the earthly and dark wiſedome of man; and Chriſt Jeſus is the light, and this was the miſtery which was hid from ages and generations, which was within the Saints, their hope of glory: and thou and all the world that denies the light of Chriſt within, and ſtumbles at the light, are ſtrangers to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of promiſe, and art without God in the world in the ſin and diſobedience upon whom the wrath of God abides: and thou cannot eſcape the judgements of God, nor ever come from under the curſe untill the light thou doſt own to guid and lead thee in the way which is pure, out of the Kingdom of darkneſs into the Kingdom of the dear Son of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> VI. <hi>Whether ſuch men who walk up according to the teſtimony of the Scriptures in the life and power of them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of light they have received; and yet through the weakneſſe of the fleſh do commit ſome ſin, though not will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, whether you can pronounce ſuch men children of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe who walk up according to the Scriptures in the life and power according to the meaſure of light they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, are kept from the ſin abiding in the light, for he that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides in the light ſins not; he that ſins hath not ſeen him neither knows him: he that doth righteouſneſſe is of God, and he that commit ſin is of the devil, as the Scripture declareth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 7. <hi>Whether all men and women that have forſaken the rule of the Scriptures, and have betaken themſelves to walk by the light within them, are made preſently perfect from ſin up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their owning of the light within; and ſo cannot ſin any more while they live in this fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Scriptures are not forſaken by thoſe who own
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118631:16"/>the light, but with the light the words are owned: and all thoſe denyed, who talk of the good words and profeſſe the Scriptures to be their rule, but live not in the pure life, but walk contrary to the Scriptures; and as there is a waiting in the light, there is a growth up from ſtrength to ſtrength, and from glory to glory un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the perfect day: But thoſe who live in the fleſh cannot preaſe God, whoſe faith is not perfect, but is reprobate concerning the faith of Chriſt, and ſuch cannot believe that ever they ſhall be made perfect or free from ſin while they live upon the earth; and without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> VIII. <hi>VVhether or no the first Reſurrection ſpoken of</hi> Revel. 20.6. <hi>be in this life yea or nay? And if it be whether hath all that walk by the light within them part in the first re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection ſo ſoon as they own that light; and if they have then whether or no is it not poſſible that they may forſake the light, and walk in darkneſſe, and ſo come to caſt of the ſecond death, which they that come to partake of the firſt reſurrection ſhall never caſt of; or is not the teſtimony of that place of Scripture true?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Concerning the firſt reſurrection ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. it is not in that life that thou lives in, which gave forth theſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: But thoſe who dwelt in the light, and were in the faith had paſſed from death to life, and in the new life it is known which is in Chriſt Jeſus, who is the reſurrection and the life, on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power, and ſuch hath part in the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and are bleſſed: But thou haſt wronged the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo it ſhall be a witneſſe againſt thee, which teſtimony is true witneſſed by the ſame ſpirit that gave forth the Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> IX. <hi>VVhether or no that body of fleſh of Chriſt that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered at Ieruſalem upon the Croſs, which Joſeph of Arithma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea begged of Pilate, and buried in his own ſepulchre, roſe again the</hi> 3. <hi>day after it was buried, whether the ſame body of fleſh be now glorified in Heaven with the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe few Queries I have written unto you who are called by the name of</hi> Quakers, <hi>I have not written them to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon of you, but to whomſoever of you ſhall be free to give me an anſwer of them in particular in truth, according to your underſtanding in them, I have not written them in any intent, but onely to be better informed in things wherein I am not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118631:16"/>in things wherein I am not ſatisfied from him who wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth good to all and hurt to none</hi> Richard Stephens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this query thou art diſputing and querying about the body of Jeſus, as the devil diſputed about the body of Moſes: But it is a miſtery hid from all dark underſtandings who hate the light that comes from Jeſus, which is the eye that ſees him who is inviſible, which all who love their evill deeds and hate the light, never ſhall know nor ſee, but are ſhut out and with the light condemned: Thou muſt firſt own the light that ſhewes thee the body of ſin, and ſo paſs through the death of the croſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the body of ſin is put of and crucified: then ſhalt thou know with what body Chriſt is glorified in Heaven with the Father. Godlineſs is a great miſtery not known to the world nor to the earthly wiſedom, but the ſecrets of God are with them that fear him; the ſpirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep and hidden things of God: So in the fear of God I do exhort thee to return unto God, and mind that principle of God in thee, that reproves thee in ſecret for thy evill deeds, there is thy Teacher if thou love it, to guide thee to God, but if thou hate it, and live according to the courſe of this world, it will be thy comdemnation: Prize thy time while thou haſt it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VVritten by one who is a lover of all thoſe that love the truth in ſimplicity and ſincerity of heart, who is known to the world by the name of <hi>Alexander Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> but hath a new name which the world knows not; written in the Book of Life.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
